Guide to the Aaron J. Vanderpoel [Papers]
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Aaron J. Vanderpoel Papers,
1837-1885.
Vanderpoel, Aaron J., 1825-1887.
ca. 300 items (1 box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079433
Biographical Note
New York lawyer. Vanderpoel specialized in corporation and municipal law.
Scope and Content
The incoming correspondence of Vanderpoel, containing letters from friends, clients, and colleagues and dealing with personal and legal matters. Correspondents include Henry M. Alexander, William Allen Butler, John P. and William V.S. Beekman, G.W. Bulkey, Joseph H. Choate, Frederic R. Coudert, Lewis L. Delafield, Jay Gould, William D.F. Maurice, Edward Pierpont, J. Bryce Smith, John Van Alen, John and Thomas Van Buren, and Henry Vanorden. Letters of a personal and business nature from various family members include several from Aaron and John Vanderpoel and Lewis Oakley, his uncles, and from Henry C. Van Schaack, his father-in-law. There are approximately twelve manuscripts of essays and speeches by A.J. Vanderpoel while he attended Kinderhook Academy and New York University, as well as a few by other family members. Various documents including mortgages, deeds, indentures, agreements, and court records relate to Vanderpoel's law practice and to family property.
Subjects
Kinderhook Academy--Students.; New York University--Students.; Alexander, Henry Martyn, d. 1899.; Butler, William Allen, 1825-1902.; Beekman, John P.; Beekman, William V. S.; Bulkey, G. W.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917.; Coudert, Frederic R. (Frederic René), 1832-1903.; Delafield, Lewis L. (Lewis Livingston), 1834-1883.; Gould, Jay, 1836-1892.; Maurice, William D. F.; Pierpont, Edward.; Smith, J. Bryce.; Van Alen, John.; Van Buren, 1810-1866.; Van Buren, Thomas.; Vanorden, Henry.; Vanderpoel, Aaron, 1799-1870.; Vanderpoel, John.; Oakley, Lewis.; Van Schaack, Henry Cruger, 1802-1887.; Kinderhook (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Families--New York (State); Schools--New York (State)--Kinderhook.; Real property--New York (State); Law offices--New York (State)--New York.; Lawyers.
Access Restriction
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
M-59
- Series I: Correspondence
  - n.d. and 1837
  - 1848 - 1849
  - 1850 -1859
  - 1864 -1867
  - 1873 -1879
  - 1880 -1884
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Vanderpoel, A. J.:
  - Essays & speeches while attending Kinderhook Academy and N.Y.U. (1840-45)
  - Vanderpoel, John & Oakley, E.B. - Essays (1850-53)
- Series III: Documents & Printed Material
  - Vanderpoel, A. J .related to his-law practice:
    - Cockroft Case
    - Raritan & Delaware Bay Railroad
    - Miscellaneous
  - Vanderpoel & Oakley families:
  - Deeds, mortgages etc.
  - Printed matter (includes memorabilia)
  - Empty envelopes